A Guide to the G. Burke Johnston Papers, 1900-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
G. Burke Johnston Papers, 1900-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1983-005
4.0 cu. ft. 8 boxes
Papers--including correspondence, subject files, printed materials, and photographs--of George Burke Johnston, literary scholar and faculty member / administrator at Virginia Tech and the University of Alabama; U.S. Army officer; poet; author; artist; and printer.
Johnston, G. Burke, (George Burke), 1907-1995
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The G. Burke Johnston Papers were donated to Special Collections in several accruals, dated 1985, 1988, and 1990-1993.
Biographical Note
George Burke Johnston, the son of George D. and Eleanor McCorvey Johnston, was born in Tuscaloosa, Alabama, on September 8, 1907. After graduating from the University of Alabama (BA, 1929), Johnston obtained his master's and doctoral degrees in English from Columbia University (1930 and 1943, respectively). In 1936, he married Mary Tabb Lancaster (1916-2003), the daughter of Dabney S. Lancaster; the Johnstons would have four children. Johnston served as an English instructor at Virginia Tech from 1930 until 1933, when he returned to the University of Alabama to join the English Department as a professor.
Johnston became a well known Shakespearean scholar as well as an expert on English dramatist/poet Ben Jonson, about whom he wrote his dissertation and published two books: Ben Jonson, Poet (1945) and The Poems of Ben Jonson (1955). He held fellowships at Columbia University, Folger Shakespeare Library, and the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies.
Johnston's tenure at Alabama was interrupted by World War II, during which he served as a major in the U. S. Army. Following active duty, he returned to Alabama an assistant professor of English before being named assistant dean of arts and sciences. In 1950, he was named dean of applied science and business administration at Virginia Tech. He was appointed dean of science and general studies in 1961, and in 1963 became the first dean of the university's College of Arts and Sciences, a position in which he served until 1966, when he was named C. P. Miles Professor of English. He retired in 1974.
In his later years, Johnston maintained a number of personal interests. He continued to publish books on his interests, editing Poems by William Camden (1975) and writing Thomas Chalmers McCorvey: Teacher, Poet, Historian (1985), a biography of his maternal grandfather. Johnston operated a home printing press on which he published his works, issuing them under the name White Rhinoceros Press. He was a skilled artist, working in pencil, paint, clay, and wood; and was licensed as an Epicopal lay minister. George Burke Johnston died on January 1, 1995.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of George Burke Johnston, an English professor and administrator at Virginia Tech and the University of Alabama; literary scholar; poet; author; artist; printer; and U. S. Army officer. The collection includes typescripts and proof copies of several of Johnston's books, as well as correspondence with editors and publishers relating to same. The correspondence files also include letters exchanged with friends and fellow scholars. Also within the collection are drafts and printed copies of Johnston's shorter works (poems, essays, and book reviews) and copies of works printed by him under his own imprint, White Rhinoceros Press. Johnston's interest in the fine arts is represented in materials relating to theatrical productions and other events, and his military career is documented in a set of files containing personnel records, orders, correspondence, and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
Series I. Writings, 1945-1992. Contained in this series are drafts and proofs of Johnston's books (including Alabama Historical Sketches, which he edited), as well as various book reviews, essays, poetry, and speeches. Included among the poems and essays are some of the works he published as White Rhinoceros Press. Major titles arranged alphabetically, followed by smaller works, arranged by genre.
Series II. Military, 1925-1967. Johnston's association with the U.S. Army is documented in this series. Included are personnel and retirement records, orders, certificates, and printed materials, as well as both official and personal correspondence. The photographs in the series relate not only to Johnston's military service but his later attendance as a college administrator visiting ROTC Summer Camp at Fort Meade, Maryland and Fort Knox, Kentucky. Arranged by document type.
Series III. Theater and Fine Arts, 1900-1983. This series contains materials relating to Johnston's interest in the arts. Much of the series is comprised of promotional materials for theatrical production companies whom Johnston was likely instrumental in securing for performances at Virginia Tech. Theatrical companies arranged alphabetically, preceding general materials at the end of the series.
Series IV. Subject / Correspondence Files, 1904-1993. This series relates mostly to Johnston's literary scholarship, published works, personal relationships, interest in printing and art, and his duties as a faculty and college administrator, particularly including his involvement in extracurricular activities at Virginia Tech. Included are letters, printed materials, and photographs from friends, colleagues, editors, and publishers. Johnston's literary interests included, but were not limited to, Shakespeare, Ben Johnson, William Camden, and J. R. R. Tolkien. (The collection contains only photocopies of letters to Johnston from Tolkien and his daughter Priscilla. Special Collections does not hold the original letters.) A single folder bearing Johnston's name contains a few pieces of biographical material, photographs, and a number of sketches and small watercolors executed by him. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent / subject, though materials relating to a single topic may appear in several different folders.
Series V. Microfilm, 1952-1972. This series is comprised of microfilm copies of rare literary works made for Johnston during the course of his research. The series contains selected pages from a number of works from Elizabethan and Stuart England, with a particular focus on poems by Ben Jonson.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Gridiron Guide. Blacksburg, VA: Virginia Tech Athletic Association, 1969. (LD5655 A3 T42 1969 VPI Spec)
Davis, Jefferson. Relations of States. Baltimore: J. Murphy & Co., 1860. (E438 D261 c. 2 Civil War Spec)
Leary, Lewis, ed. Mark Twain's Letters to Mary. New York: Columbia University Press, 1961. [inscribed by the ed.] (PS1331 A3 R6 c.2 Large Spec)
The following item was removed from the collection and added to the Historical Map Collection:
Map of James River, Virginia and Vicinity: Virginia Navigation Company. E. A. Barber, Jr. 1899.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I. Writings, 1945-1992
  - Alabama Historical Sketches typescript, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-1)
  - A Brief Review of the First Half-Century of the Alpha Omicron Circle of Omicron Delta Kappa, 1983 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Ben Jonson: Poet typescript draft, 1945 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Ben Jonson: Poet proofs, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Poems by William Camden typescript [photocopy], n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Poems of Ben Jonson typescript draft, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Poems of Ben Jonson proof, 1954 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - "Thomas Chalmers McCorvey" first draft, n.d., [4 folders] (Box-folder 2-2)
  - "Thomas Chalmers McCorvey" second draft, n.d., [3 folders] (Box-folder 2-3 to 3-1)
  - Thomas Chalmers McCorvey: Teacher, Poet, Historian [final draft], 1985, [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Thomas Chalmers McCorvey: Teacher, Poet, Historian galley proof, 1985, [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Book reviews, 1948-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Essays, 1967-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Poetry, 1949-1992, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Speeches and sermons, 1970-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 4-1)
- Series II. Military, 1925-1967
  - Records, 1925-1967 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1953, n.d. (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Photographs, 1943-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Printed material, 1941-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 4-5)
- Series III. Theater and Fine Arts, 1900-1983
  - Cleveland Play House, n.d. (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Grass Roots Opera / National Opera Company, 1953-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 4-7)
  - National Players, 1961-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Players, Inc. / University Players, 1952-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 4-9-10)
  - Event programs and ephemera, 1940-1983, n.d. (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Sheet music, 1900-1924, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Viscomi, Joseph, Playing with the Toy Theatre, 1977 (Box-folder 5-2)
- Series IV. Subject / Correspondence Files, 1904-1993
  - Aa-Ak (Box-folder 5-3)
    - Adams, Philip R., 1952-1982
    - Akers, Fannie Louise, 1976-1985, n.d.
  - Ala (Box-folder 5-4)
    - Alabama Historical Sketches, 1947-1971
  - Alb-Au (Box-folder 5-5)
    - Albert, Ray Allen, 1982
    - American Association of University Professors, 1946-1959
    - American Book Company, 1951
    - Austin Peay State University site visit, 1973
  - Av-Az (Box-folder 5-6)
    - Ayres, Harry Morgan, 1932-1964, n.d.
  - Ba-Bem (Box-folder 5-7)
    - Barnwell, Charles and Lucile, 1929-1964, n.d.
    - Beattie, William, 1966
    - Beckwith, Claudia, 1991
    - Belser, Karl, 1933, n.d.
  - Ben (Box-folder 5-8)
    - Ben Jonson: Poet, 1940-1973, n.d.
  - Beo-Bz (Box-folder 5-9)
    - Bridges, George, n.d.
    - Brown, Ralph M., 1934-1958, n.d.
    - Byers, John R. Jr., 1965-1987
  - Ca-Cg (Box-folder 5-10)
    - Camden, William, 1969-1979, n.d.
  - Ch-Clh (Box-folder 5-11)
    - Christiansburg Book Club, 1976
    - Chute, Marchette, 1951-1975, n.d.
    - The Citadel, 1964
    - Claiborne, Jerry D., 1989
    - Clarkson, Jack Jolly, 1925-1970, n.d.
    - Claytor, Graham, 1965
  - Cli-Clz (Box-folder 5-12)
    - Clifford, James L., 1935-1978, n.d.
  - Cm-Cz (Box-folder 5-13)
    - Coblentz, Stanton A., 1941-1966, n.d.
    - Collier's Encyclopedia, 1960-1980
    - Collins, LeRoy, 1960
    - Cornelius, Roberta D., 1972
    - Cornish, George A., 1950
  - Da-Dt (Box-folder 5-14)
    - de Chezeau, Eunice, 1992-1993
    - De Launay, Paul, 1949
    - Dearing, Bruce, 1965-1979
    - Derring, Paul N., 1959-1972, n.d.
    - Devine, John M., 1961-[1970]
    - Dietrick, Leander B., 1970-1975, n.d.
    - Dobbie, Elliott V. K., 1959
  - Du-Dz (Box-folder 5-15)
    - Duff, James, 1957-1971
    - Duke University, 1979
  - E (Box-folder 5-16)
    - Eastman School of Music, 1939
    - Emory and Henry College, 1970
    - Episcopal Church, 1941-1973
  - Fa-Fn (Box-folder 5-17)
    - Fidler, William Perry, 1980-1988
  - Foa-Foq (Box-folder 5-18)
    - Folger Shakespeare Library, 1952-1978, n.d.
  - For-Fz (Box-folder 6-1)
    - Fort, Joseph, 1959-1984, n.d.
    - Fountain, Alvin M., 1966
  - G (Box-folder 6-2)
    - Godfrey, Albert Blanton, 1968
    - Grafton, Martha S., 1964
    - Greet, Cabell, 1946-1957
  - Ha-Hov (Box-folder 6-3)
    - Hall, Jay, 1956-1966
    - Hall, Robert A. Jr., 1978-1986, n.d.
    - Harbage, Alfred, 1963
    - Harp, Richard, 1990
    - Harper and Row, 1978-1986
    - Hays, Brooks, 1963
    - Hispanic Society of America, 1982
    - Hodnett, Ted, 1956
  - How-Hoz (Box-folder 6-4)
    - Howard, Warren W. 1904-1916
  - Ja-Joh (Box-folder 6-5)
    - Johnston, George Burke, 1925-1989, n.d.
  - Joi-Jz (Box-folder 6-6)
    - Jones, William M., 1963-1966
    - Justice, R. Glen, 1974
  - K (Box-folder 6-7)
    - Kathe, Barbara A., 1978
    - Kilpatrick, James J. "Jack", 1953-1955
    - Kirk, Russell, 1990-1991
    - Knote, Theodore W., 1935
    - Knower, Henry McElderry, 1928-1940, n.d.
    - Kohler, Dayton, 1962, n.d.
  - La-Lh (Box-folder 6-8)
    - Lancaster, Dabney S., 1950
    - Lawrence, William Witherle, 1930-1956
    - Leary, Lewis, 1956-1965
    - Lee, Lawrence, 1956-1965
    - Lee, Robert E., 1960-1981
    - Legh-Jones, John, 1935
  - Li (Box-folder 6-9)
    - Literature and printing, 1928-1963
  - Lj-Lz (Box-folder 6-10)
    - Long, George, 1979-1985
    - Longwood College, 1978
    - Lowe, G. Burman, 1958
  - Ma-Mb (Box-folder 6-11)
    - Mason, August H., 1941-1980, n.d.
  - Mc-Mz (Box-folder 6-12)
    - [McCorvey, Thomas Chalmers], 1925
    - McManaway, James G. "Mac", 1945-1976
    - Milton, Hilary, 1959-1978
    - Modern Language Association of America, 1952-1974, n.d.
    - Moore, Adam G. N., 1958-1986
  - N-O (Box-folder 6-13)
    - Omicron Delta Kappa, 1941-1983, n.d.
  - Pa-Pn (Box-folder 6-14)
    - Pannell, Anne G., 1953-1956
    - Payne, Al, 1958-1973
    - Pendergrass, R. N., 1974
    - Phi Kappa Phi, 1966-1974
  - Poa-Poem (Box-folder 6-15)
    - The Poems of Ben Jonson, 1951-1966
  - Poen-Poez (Box-folder 6-16)
    - Poetry and essays, 1941-1975
  - Pof-Pz (Box-folder 7-1)
    - Poole, Elisha C., 1952
    - Prouty, Charles Tyler, 1953
    - Public engagements, 1956-1979
  - Q-Rn (Box-folder 7-2)
    - Radford Review, 1960-1966
    - Raugh, Miriam Joseph (Sister), 1956-1963
  - Roa-Rom (Box-folder 7-3)
    - Roberts, Ruby Altizer, 1954-1969
    - Rodriguez, Louis J., 1974
  - Ron-Rou (Box-folder 7-4)
    - Routledge and Kegan Paul Ltd., 1951-1983, n.d.
  - Row-Rz (Box-folder 7-5)
    - Rowe, C. Eugene, 1950-1975
    - Ruff, William, 1946
  - Sa-Sp (Box-folder 7-6)
    - Scaglione, Aldo, 1972
    - Seay, Raleigh F. Jr. "Sandy", 1989
    - Shakespeare, William, 1964-1987
    - Simpson, Percy, 1943-1955
    - Southern Conference, 1964
    - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 1968-1969
    - Southwestern Louisiana Institute, 1955-1956
    - Sparkman, John, 1950-1952
  - Sq-Stt (Box-folder 7-7)
    - Strode, Hudson, 1950-1970, n.d.
  - Stu-Sz (Box-folder 7-8)
    - Studies in Philology, 1974-1979
    - Sullivan, A. M., 1962-1966
    - Sumner, Laura V., 1962
  - Ta-Tm (Box-folder 7-9)
    - Taylor, Henry, 1972-1973
    - ten Hoor, Marten, 1952-1953
    - Texas Agricultural and Mechanical University, 1963, n.d.
  - Tn-Tz (Box-folder 7-10)
    - Tolkien, J. R. R., 1964-1970, n.d., [no original letters; photocopies only]
    - Tolkien, Priscilla, 1982-1983, [no original letters; photocopies only]
    - Trinity College, University of Dublin, n.d.
  - Ua-University of M (Box-folder 7-11)
    - University of Alabama, 1929-1987, n.d.
  - University of N-Uz (Box-folder 7-12)
    - University of Virginia, 1937-1978, n.d.
  - Va-Vh (Box-folder 7-13)
    - Van Doren, Mark, 1959-1962
    - Vanderbilt University, 1991
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute correspondence, 1930-1989 (Box-folder 7-14)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute events and photographs, 1953-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 7-15)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute Founders Day, 1977-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 8-1)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute Visiting Scholars Program, 1951-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 8-2)
  - Wa-Wek (Box-folder 8-3)
    - Weber, Kurt, 1934-1935, n.d.
  - Wel-Wg (Box-folder 8-4)
    - Wells, Henry W. and Katherine, 1932-1992, n.d., [2 folders]
  - Wh (Box-folder 8-5)
    - White Rhinoceros Press, 1961-1979, n.d.
  - Wi-Z and unidentified (Box-folder 8-6)
    - Wilson, I. D., 1958-1977
    - Wilson, James Southall, 1955
    - Wilson, John Delane, 1980-1983
    - Wragg, T. S., 1967, n.d.
    - Wu, Blanche Ching-Yi, 1980, n.d.
    - Wyllie, John Cook, 1953-1966
    - "Bob" (Oxford University Press), 1950
    - "Gregory" (Edinburgh, Scotland), 1971
- Series V. Microfilm, 1952-1972 (Box-folder 8-7)
  - Anglica Hibernica (selected pages) (1602), 1972 (Reel 1)
  - Camden's Britannia (selected pages) (1607), 1959 (Reel 1)
  - Coryat's Crudities (selected pages) (n.d.), 1959 (Reel 1)
  - "The Life of Mr. Camden" (from Britannia) (1745), 1971 (Reel 2)
  - Exequiae Illustrissimi Equitis (1587), n.d. (Reel 3)
  - Ben Jonson poetry (selections) (1600-1634), n.d. (Reel 4)
  - Ben Jonson poetry (selections) (1600-1692, n.d.), 1952 (Reel 5)